<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Greg Alonge</title><link href="/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="/feeds/all.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>/</id><updated>2019-12-24T10:00:00-08:00</updated><entry><title>How Article II Literalism Can Shield Against Despotism</title><link href="/literalism-against-despotism.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2019-12-24T10:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2019-12-24T10:00:00-08:00</updated><author><name>Gregory Alonge</name></author><id>tag:None,2019-12-24:/literalism-against-despotism.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;style&gt;
  .indented {
    text-indent: 30pt;
  }
&lt;/style&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=indented&gt;In 1812, Emperor Napoleon Bonaparte singularly and needlessly waged war on Russia.  He amassed an army of over 600,000 soldiers and pushed forth toward the river Neman.  Once he crossed that Rubicon, he had again, singularly, committed himself and the lives of the French people to an unfathomably horrendous bloodbath.  After hypothermia, starvation, disease and enemy slaughter ravaged the &lt;i&gt;Grand Armée&lt;/i&gt;, less than 200,000 soldiers lived to return to France.  The stragglers were so ravished that after gorging themselves with food for the first time in months, another nearly 100,000 soldiers died from their …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;style&gt;
  .indented {
    text-indent: 30pt;
  }
&lt;/style&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=indented&gt;In 1812, Emperor Napoleon Bonaparte singularly and needlessly waged war on Russia.  He amassed an army of over 600,000 soldiers and pushed forth toward the river Neman.  Once he crossed that Rubicon, he had again, singularly, committed himself and the lives of the French people to an unfathomably horrendous bloodbath.  After hypothermia, starvation, disease and enemy slaughter ravaged the &lt;i&gt;Grand Armée&lt;/i&gt;, less than 200,000 soldiers lived to return to France.  The stragglers were so ravished that after gorging themselves with food for the first time in months, another nearly 100,000 soldiers died from their debilitated bodies’ inability to digest the food.  All said, less than 100,000 soldiers lived the tell the gruesome tale, all because one despot had complete and tyrannical control over his nation.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=indented&gt;
Of course in 1812 the United States had just recently become an independent nation; however, similar stories of the downfall of tyranny had made an impression on the Framers’ mind, causing them to create an Executive with undoubtedly limited powers.  Indeed, Article II of the constitution is relatively minuscule when compared to article I.  The message was clear: despots lead to despotism—tyrants lead to tyranny.  We must also remember that the U.S. had fought for its independence against a monarchy, a monarchy which was seen as having suffocated the liberty out of the colonists.  All this in mind, the scope of Executive branch power becomes crucial in our constitutional discourse.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=indented&gt;
Perhaps the most important supreme court case to address this discussion was &lt;i&gt;Youngstown Sheet &amp; Tube CO. v. Sawyer&lt;/i&gt; (1952).  In it, differing theories on the scope of Executive power was articulated, and these theories have served as the framework within which constitutional law has operated ever since.  Here, I will be outlining the different theories, and how they have been applied to four other important supreme court cases.  Ultimately, I argue that we must abide by Justice Black’s literalist jurisprudence to protect our liberties and stave off Executive tyranny.  The only flexibility we should permit in this literalism is when that flexibility is designed to limit the Executive even further, as the prospect of an overpowering Executive threatens to curtail our liberties at any moment.  Such is the nature of a leader: to seek out such power, and such is the nature of the social corpus: to give it over to him.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=indented&gt;
In 1952, the Korean War was at full steam.  Labor disputes threatened the production of our nation’s steel which was a perceived threat to national security that President Truman could not accept.  As a result, Truman issued an Executive order, seizing control of steel production.  He argued that the stoppage of the steel production would immediately and seriously threaten national security, as steel was a crucial resource needed to fight the war in Korea.  In Youngstown Sheet &amp; Tube CO. v. Sawyer, the courts decided whether or not such an Executive action was constitutional.  Delivering the opinion of the court, Justice Black held that this act by the Executive was unconstitutional because  Presidential power must derive from either a Congressional statute or an expressed constitutional authority within article II.  Since, Black argued, Congress had given the President no such authority, “[i]t [was] clear that if the President had authority to issue the order he did, it must be found in some provisions of the constitution” (324).  Black held that no such provision existed, as the provision granting the President Commander in Chief of the armed forces did not grant him the power to “...take possession of private property to keep labor disputes from stopping production” (324).  He argued that such an act is tantamount to lawmaking, and lawmaking is expressly the job of the legislature, not the Executive, who carries those laws out.  As such, Truman’s order was deemed unconstitutional and struck down.  This line of reasoning has come to define the ‘literalist approach,’ which only allows Executive powers which are expressly enumerated in the constitution.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=indented&gt;
Justice Jackson offered a concurring opinion, but his line of reasoning provided more breathing room for Presidential power in future instances.  Jackson outlined a three-part ‘workable government approach.’  First, he states that the President's “authority is at its maximum” when he “acts pursuant to an express or implied authorization of Congress” (325).  Truman’s Executive order did not fall within this first category, because there was no Congressional statute giving Truman such authority.  Second, if the President acts neither pursuant to nor in violation of a Congressional statute, there is a bit of a grey area, or “zone of twilight” in which the President should only act if there is an imperative to do so.  Truman’s actions did not fall under this category either, because Congress had not been silent on the matter; rather, they had passed three different statutes addressing the labor issue at hand.  Lastly, the President's power “is at its lowest ebb” when “the President takes measures incompatible with the expressed or implied will of Congress…” (325)  Here, according to Jackson, is where Truman’s Executive order lay, and as such, Jackson concurred that this Executive order was unconstitutional.  However, as we can see, Jackson’s three categories give an Executive far more flexibility in taking action as compared to Black’s literalist approach.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=indented&gt;
Justice Douglas also concurred with the opinion of the court, warning us that, “[a] Executive power—from the reign of ancient kings to the rule of modern dictators—has the outward appearance of efficiency” (326).  However, Douglass introduced a third way of approaching this question of Executive scope.  He argued that when an Executive has been granted certain powers outside of the constitution for a significant period of time, these powers, “may be treated as gloss on ‘Executive power’...” (329)  This can be seen as another form of workable government approach, which acknowledges that some traditions of Executive power become ingrained in our way of governing, and such traditions should be added onto the spirit of the constitution.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=indented&gt;
Lastly, Chief Justice Vinson leads the dissent, arguing that extraordinary times call for extraordinary measures, and “these [were] extraordinary times” (329).  Vinson claims that as the nation’s Commander in Chief, Truman had the authority to seize the mills because action was required to protect our country.  Military operations can take strange forms in extraordinary times, and in 1952, it took the form of taking control of the steel mills.  Simply put, stoppage of the steel mills put the country in a position of insecurity, and it is the job of the Commander in Chief to ensure the security of the nation.  As far as Executive reach is concerned, Vinson’s position represents the most flexible in terms of granting Executive powers.  His position essentially allows the President to do whatever he feels necessary to ensure our security.  As I argue, this affords the Executive far too much authority, because it is in the nature of the Executive to amass power, and of the populace to want to cede power to the Executive to feel more secure.  This nature is of course short sighted, as it ends up creating a despot who threatens our liberty.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=indented&gt;
Now we examine the line-item-veto, and the court case which addresses its constitutionality: &lt;i&gt;Clinton v. City of New York&lt;/i&gt; (1998).  The City of New York argued that the President does not have the authority to strike down only parts of a bill, but rather, he could either veto the whole thing or not veto it at all.  Justice Stevens speaking on behalf of the majority agreed, employing an approach akin to Justice Black’s literalism.  He says, “there is no provision in the constitution that authorizes the President to enact, to amend, or to repeal statutes” (338).  Literally following the letter of the constitution, President Clinton had no authority to strike down only a component of a bill.  Justice Kennedy reinforces the decision of the majority by reminding us how important separation of powers is in protecting our liberties.  He points out that “[t]he Constitution's structure requires a stability which transcends the convenience of the moment” (339).  He asks us to envision a world in which we capriciously changed the content of the constitution to suit us however we think best at the moment.  Such instability would be counterproductive, and most importantly, It would jeopardize our most sacred values, such as liberty.  Justice Breyer leads the dissent by making an interesting argument appealing to prudence.  The dissent points out that at the time of our Framers, the scope of each bill passed by Congress was minuscule in comparison to modern times.  Therefore, the Presidents of the past could easily veto a bill summarily knowing that they disagreed with the entirety of the bill.  Contemporarily bills, on the other hand, contain hundreds, sometimes thousands of pages of meticulous details.  Therefore, it only makes sense that the President can choose to rid a bill of certain particulars while simultaneously choosing to keep the rest of it.  It is not prudent to throw away an entire bill simply because the President disagrees with a few minor details, as was the case here with Clinton.  Furthermore, the dissent argues that the courts ought not “referee a dispute among the other two branches” (340).  The dissent's position is much more akin to Jackson’s three-part workable government approach.  Specifically, this would fit into Jackson’s first category, as here the President was acting in line with a Congressional statute, namely the Line Item Veto Act.  Jackson would argue that since Congress delegated this power to the President, the President was well within his authority to act pursuant to the wishes of Congress.  However, Jackson’s workable government approach is far too flexible, because what if the party of the Executive happens to control both the House and the Senate?  Given Jackson’s reasoning, this would enable Congress to essentially give the President a blank check via statute.  Such latitude provides little safeguard against despotism—a safeguard crucial in combating the populace’s tendency to give their liberty over to a President hungry for power in exchange for security (in a Hobbesian quid pro quo).
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=indented&gt;
Next, we discuss the power of appointments.  In &lt;i&gt;Morrison v. Olson&lt;/i&gt; (1988), Chief Justice Rehnquist speaking on behalf of the majority held that Congressional appointment of an independent counsel to investigate certain members of the Executive branch was constitutional.  He bases this opinion in the appointments clause of Article II which states that “Congress may by law vest the appointment of such inferior officers, as they think proper, in the President alone, in the courts, or in the heads of departments” (Article II, § 2, Cl. 2).  Here, Congress argues that they have vested appointment power of an inferior officer (the independent counsel) in the courts, which has dispatched this independent counsel within the Executive.  The key distinction here is whether or not the appointment in question is an ‘inferior’ position or a ‘principal’ position.  If the latter, only the President would have the authority to appoint such a position.  Justice Rehnquist found that the special counsel falls under the distinction of an inferior officer, and thus, Congress has the authority to vest appointment power with the courts.  He reasons that this is because 1) the council is “subject to removal by a higher Executive Branch official” (358).  2)  The council has a limited function.  3) The council's jurisdiction is limited, And 4) the counsel’s tenure is limited as well.  All of these details render the independent counsel an inferior office in the eyes of the majority, and thus, Congress has authority to vest in the courts this appointment power.  Such a position would have to be classified under Black’s literalist approach, as it takes the appointments clause literally to the word, thus not granting the President any extra power.  In his fervent dissent, Justice Scalia vehemently claims that the decision violates the separation of powers principle.  Scalia argues that Congress has ostensibly vested an Executive power in the courts, which violates article II, which states that “the Executive power shall be vested in the President of the united states”  (Article II, § 1, Cl. 1).  In other words, the independent counsel holds Executive power, but all Executive power is vested in the President, and the President did not appoint the independent counsel.  Thus violating article, I § 1, Cl. 1.  This is because “[g]overnmental investigation and prosecution of crimes is a quintessentially Executive function” (359).  In short, Scalia finds this to be a dangerously slippery slope ending in blurred lines between the three government spheres.  Fitting Scalia’s position into any one larger theory is difficult.  It could be argued that it fits Black's literalism because he is claiming to interpret the constitution literally.  It could also be argued that Scalia is echoing Jackson’s third category, arguing that even when the President is always empowered to exercise his enumerated powers even when acting counter to a Congressional statute.  Ultimately, this is where there should be a little breathing room in within literalism.  Both sides argue that they are reading the constitution literally, although, Scalia’s argument seems to be more technically literal.  However, oversight of the potentially tyrannical Executive is a must, for, this is the branch most susceptible to despotism. Therefore, Justice Rehnquist's quasi-literalist reading is rightfully adopted here, because it is a literalism that is flexible enough to hold the Executive accountable.  Such a paradigm does not fit squarely into Black, Jackson, or Douglas’ theories, as it seeks only limited flexibility &lt;i&gt;when that flexibility is intended to thwart tyranny within the Executive&lt;/i&gt;.  Which is a dangerous prospect, as the populace is so eager to give over their liberties in exchange for security, and when security itself is so easily made to be fleeting by a power-thirsty executive.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=indented&gt;
The question of Executive scope extends to formal recognition of foreign sovereignties as well.  Such was the case in &lt;i&gt;Zivotofsky v. Kerry&lt;/i&gt; (2015).  Congress had passed a statute allowing U.S. citizens born in Jerusalem to list ‘Israel’ as their birthplace on their passports.  The Secretary of State refused to comply with this statute, arguing that such a Congressional mandate amounted to Congress forcing the President to recognize Israel as a foreign sovereignty, and only the President alone could declare such a recognition.  Speaking for the majority, Justice Kennedy argued that such a statute was unconstitutional because it robbed the Executive of an exclusive function.  Kennedy acknowledges that here, the President was within Jackson’s 3rd category, giving him the least amount of latitude to act.  Nonetheless, since the constitution gives the Executive exclusive and conclusive power to recognize foreign states, reasoned Kennedy, Congress had no authority to demand that the Executive recognize Israel as a state.  Chief Justice Roberts and Justice Alito disagree that the language of Article II gives the Executive exclusive and conclusive recognition power.  They argue in their dissent that such language amounts to Executive duties, not powers.  Therefore, the President has a duty to receiving ambassadors, for example, but this in no way implies a power of state recognition.  Moreover, they argue, simply stating a birthplace as Jerusalem on a passport is not tantamount to formal recognition of a country.  Identification does not equate to recognition.  In another dissent, Justice Scalia echoes these sentiments, saying “[i]t is utterly impossible for this deference to private requests to constitute an act that unequivocally manifests an intention to grant recognition” (393).  Furthermore, Scalia points out that Congress has the authority to ‘establish a uniform Rule of Naturalization” (Article I, § 8 Cl. 4).  He argues that regulating passports falls under this authority. Therefore the Executive must honor the actions of Congress as backed by the constitution.  The holding given by justice Kennedy represents what I would consider to be a Douglas-type Executive power gloss.  Since the President had been in charge of recognizing foreign states for so long, this power becomes glossed into the Executive's authority.  Such a holding violates Justice Black's literalism because there is more evidence within the constitution for Congress to regulate passports than for the President to have exclusive recognition power.  As Kennedy himself acknowledges, this issue falls within Justice Jackson’s 3rd category of low Presidential latitude; however, Kennedy seems to be generous towards the President, citing ambiguous evidence supporting the President’s exclusive and conclusive power.  If we fit a more literalist approach here, as I suggest we do, this decision would have been held in favor of Congress, thus forcing the Executive to honor Zivotofsky’s passport request.  Such literalism is the most effective tool for keeping the Executive in check.  This issue here on its own may be somewhat inconsequential in terms of Executive tyranny, but to give the Executive any more powers than absolutely necessary is a dangerous prospect.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=indented&gt;
We conclude with perhaps the most glaring example of potential Executive overreach: &lt;i&gt;Hamdi v. Rumsfeld&lt;/i&gt; (2004).  Petitioner and U.S. citizen Hamdi was challenging not only his classification as an ‘enemy combatant,’ but more importantly, the Executive’s authority to detain him indefinitely without due process as a result of this classification.  Justice O’Connor speaking for the majority held that the Executive was not authorized to perform such a detainment.  She reminds us that “history and common sense teach us that an unchecked system of detention carries the potential to become a means for oppression …” (407).  In her decision, she carefully weighs the values of due process and liberty against the importance of national security.  Ultimately, she makes concessions to the Executive, allowing them to admit a lower bar of evidence against Hamdi in federal courts, but she holds that Hamdi must be afforded all the due process that is rightfully his as an American citizen.  Justices Souter and Ginsberg, in part concurring and in part dissenting go a step further, arguing that Hamdi should be released pursuant to the Non-Detention Act, given the dearth of evidence against him.  They saliently remind us that “[t]he defining character of American constitutional government is its constant tension between security and liberty, serving both by partial helpings of each” (409-410).  Justice Scalia offers a somewhat simple dissent, arguing that Hamdi should be tried for treason which carries its own constitutional proceedings.  Lastly, Justice Thomas in his dissent argues that the courts should stay out of this issue entirely, and furthermore, the Executive is acting “well within its authority” because he was acting pursuant to the Congressional statute, AUMF.  Thomas’ argument lines up squarely with Jackson’s first principle, giving the Executive the greatest latitude because it was acting pursuant to a Congressional statute.  However, this argument affords the President far too much authority and completely ignores the warnings articulated by both Justice O’Connor and Souter.  They rightfully remind us how delicate the principle of liberty is, and how easily an Executive can monopolize that liberty under the guise of protection.  Justice Scalia offers what he considers to be a literalist approach, which is a more efficacious plan than Justice Thomas’ given that his approach still demands constitutional backing.  Interestingly, Justice Souter’s argument can be classified under Jackson's third category, as he sites congressional statute opposing the detainment.  Ultimately, the majority makes an important literalist decision that serves to bolster our bill of rights and protect liberty against despotic tyranny.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=indented&gt;
We have examined five different ways in which the Executive can potentially and dangerously increase his power.  Let us never forget the dangers of a despot, and always fight to protect our liberties against the threat of dictatorship.  Yes, national security is essential, but liberty-security is even more essential, as it allows us to maintain a stable state that is prepared and fortified against outside threats.  In a rare twist of events, our constitution is well-suited for such a task.  Therefore, we must adjudicate our common law system literally, only stretching that literalism &lt;i&gt;when the stretching serves to further protect us against the Executive&lt;/i&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="law"></category></entry><entry><title>Day at the Museum: The Phenomenology of My Recent Pilgrimage to Art</title><link href="/day-at-the-museum.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2019-07-27T10:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2019-07-27T10:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Gregory Alonge</name></author><id>tag:None,2019-07-27:/day-at-the-museum.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;style&gt;
  .indented {
    text-indent: 30pt;
  }
&lt;/style&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=indented&gt;In 1954, Theodor Adorno invited us to watch television with him.  While tempting, I instead opted to go to the museum with Walter Benjamin.  This past weekend, I embarked upon a pilgrimage to the J. Paul Getty Museum in West Los Angeles.  For this project, I will create a phenomenological account of that pilgrimage, as informed and illuminated by Walter Benjamin’s 1935 essay, &lt;i&gt;The Work of Art in the Age of its Technological Reproducibility&lt;/i&gt;.  To do this, I will first discuss my visit to the iconic paintings in the upper level of the West Pavilion.  I …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;style&gt;
  .indented {
    text-indent: 30pt;
  }
&lt;/style&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=indented&gt;In 1954, Theodor Adorno invited us to watch television with him.  While tempting, I instead opted to go to the museum with Walter Benjamin.  This past weekend, I embarked upon a pilgrimage to the J. Paul Getty Museum in West Los Angeles.  For this project, I will create a phenomenological account of that pilgrimage, as informed and illuminated by Walter Benjamin’s 1935 essay, &lt;i&gt;The Work of Art in the Age of its Technological Reproducibility&lt;/i&gt;.  To do this, I will first discuss my visit to the iconic paintings in the upper level of the West Pavilion.  I will then discuss my subsequent visit to the Center for Photographs downstairs in that same pavilion.  Lastly, I will take the reader down to the gift shop with me on my way out.  My account will focus on two major pieces of art: Vincent Van Gogh’s, Irises (1889), and Oscar Rejlander’s allegorical photograph montage, &lt;i&gt;The Two Ways of Life&lt;/i&gt; (1857).  By examining my interaction with these works of art and others, I will analyze Benjamin’s thesis: that the auratic nature of famous historical paintings render their effect politically impotent, while on the contrary, the effect of photography is indeed politically subversive because of its ability to display the real world as something to be molded.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=indented&gt;Last friday, I drove to the one place where unique items can always be found: the museum.  Of course, the neoclassical shrine of unique art was symbolically and literally placed at an elevation, so I embarked upon a tram ride that would slowly close the distance between the world of fungibility and the world of the originality.  Indeed, the trip felt like an ascent to the heavens, as majestically verdant views unraveled themselves from the tram windows before my eyes.  While, “[a] painting has always exerted a claim to be viewed primarily by a single person or by a few,” that was certainly not the case here (36).  Indeed, I was just one of dozens on this tram, and the tram itself was only one of hundreds for the day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=indented&gt;This, according to Benjamin, is because, “[t]he simultaneous viewing of paintings by a large audience, as happens in the 19th century, is an early symptom of the crisis in painting, a crisis triggered...by the artwork’s claim to the attention of masses” (36).  For Benjamin, at some point in the 19th century, artwork under the auspices of capitalism and its technologically reproductive fruits began to shift from cult-value to exhibition-value.  That is to say, art in its oldest and most primitive form served as a portal or intermediary between humans and the spiritual world (25).  This is not art for human perception, it’s art for spiritual connection.  But, as history unfolded and capitalism laid claim to the dominant mode of production, this ritual value increasingly gave way to exhibition value.  Then, &lt;i&gt;“[w]ith the emancipation of specific artistic practices from the service of ritual, the opportunities for exhibiting their products increase[d]”&lt;/i&gt; (25).  As a result, institutions like the Getty not only allow for large viewing audiences, they indeed facilitate it.  Thus, myself and thousands of others that day were on our way to see art for the sake of seeing art (25)&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=indented&gt;Tram at the top, I stepped off like a proverbial kid in a candy shop: so much to do, and so much to see.  Naturally, nothing was to be experienced before a leisurely bite in the bucolic manicured gardens of neatly arranged flowers and foliage.  The air seemed fresher—the food tasted sweeter.  Indeed, that was the best damn oatmeal raisin cookie I have ever had in my life.  It was almost as if something was pervading the geist, an aura of some sort.  It must have been coming from somewhere, the inclination in such moments is to find out from where.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=indented&gt;Now, the Getty has an abundance of exhibits, but for some reason, call it happenstance, call it auratic pull, I decided to enter the West Pavilion and head upstairs—I knew there were paintings up there, and I wanted paintings.  I walked through the threshold, tennis shoes squeaking with every step, turned to my right, and saw a painting mounted on the wall of ships on a marina at dawn.  My philistine sensibilities being what they are, I asked myself, “hey, isn’t that, like, a &lt;i&gt;really&lt;/i&gt; famous painting?”  I read the description, and lo, it was Claude Monet’s, &lt;i&gt;Impression, Sunrise&lt;/i&gt; (1872).  Yep, famous indeed.  I immediately felt a rush—I was penetrating the source of the aura that made my cookie sweeter.  I continued onward.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=indented&gt;Passing similar recognizable paintings, I came across an entryway to a small room with light charcoal paint, polished hardwood floors, and dozens of people bustling inside.  I was confused.  Why were so many people concentrated in this room?  There was a tour group and several people clustered in the back right corner taking pictures.  I looked at a few paintings of fruit bowls before coming across an eye-catcher:  Édouard Manet’s, &lt;i&gt;Rue Mosnier with Flags&lt;/i&gt;.  I loved it.  It was luminously intricate.  Both the bleached cobble-stoned road and the swinging tri-color flags seemed to be lit up by an unseen sun placed above the frame.  My attention was next grabbed by Monet’s, &lt;i&gt;The Portrait of Rouen Cathedral in Morning Light&lt;/i&gt;.  The more I looked at it, the more I could distinguish the ornate features of a gothic church through the dark morning fog, a gradual unveiling that compelled me to keep searching.  As I continued, my excitement mounted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=indented&gt;Finally, I made my way to the back right corner where everyone was crowded around a painting of what looked to be blue flowers with green leaves.  The awe-struck huddle was standing at a distance, which only made me want to get closer.  “[T]he urge [grew] stronger  to get a hold of [the] object at close range…” (23)  Now in between the crowd and the painting itself, I looked up and read, ‘Vincent Van Gogh, &lt;i&gt;Irises&lt;/i&gt;, (1889).’  A chill ran up my spine.  A Van Gogh!  Even I knew this was a big deal indeed.  Here it was, this room, this painting, the source of the ambiance that permeated the air of the garden and marble walkways.  It all made sense now, everyone was fixated on that piece as if stuck in time.  One particularly statuesque woman of middle-age stood there cemented in place with headphones around ears and pamphlet in hand—she wasn’t going anywhere anytime soon.  She wasn’t even looking directly at the painting. Instead, she was standing sideways to it, eyes glazed in a sort of liminal state between the floor, pamphlet, and room at large.  This woman, the other onlookers, the paintings themselves, and the sequestered nature of the place, all drove home the unique feel of this gallery, and indeed, entire museum.  But what was it that I was feeling?  According to Benjamin, I was feeling &lt;i&gt;aura&lt;/i&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=indented&gt;So what is &lt;i&gt;aura&lt;/i&gt;, for Benjamin?  It is, “[a] strange tissue of space and time: the unique apparition of a distance, however near it may be” (23).  To be clear, it was not the museum gallery that was giving off an aura, but rather, the paintings within the gallery.  Each one of them original representations of artistic genius that can never be recreated or replicated.  When Van Gogh painted &lt;i&gt;Irises&lt;/i&gt;, each brush stroke was unique to that moment in 1889, and when that moment died, it died forever.  As such, each inch of that painting is a time-capsule containing greatness that once was, but could never be again.  Benjamin reminds us that today, the uniqueness of a historical painting becomes rarer and rarer, and thus more special.  Our world, which grows continually more and more technologically reproducible, has a dearth of such precious uniqueness in art.  Templates, photography, film, television, music, graphic design: all these modern modes of art are not only reproducible, but their reproducibility is their art.  To photograph something, for example, is to reproduce a moment in space and time, and that reproduction itself &lt;i&gt;is the art&lt;/i&gt;, which in turn will be mass circulated.  As such, when we stand face-to-face with a unique and original work like &lt;i&gt;Irises&lt;/i&gt;, its aura lands that much more potently with us as spectators.  This is why I and those around me were stupefied in its presence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=indented&gt;But Benjamin is not merely commenting on phenomenological accounts of experiencing art.  Instead, he is using that phenomenology to illuminate political reality.  For Benjamin, an artwork’s aura, “...bears the mark of the history to which the work has been subject” (21).  As I said, each brush stroke of &lt;i&gt;Irises&lt;/i&gt; was a verb locked in time, 1889, to be precise.  As such, the painting encapsulates a piece of 1889 itself.  Thus, we have history at our fingertips, even if we can’t touch it.  And indeed, this is &lt;i&gt;why&lt;/i&gt; we cannot touch it, because to do so would defile the piece of history and its aura with the insignificant skin oils of today.  What we have in Irises, and the other paintings in that room is an auratic &lt;i&gt;physical embodiment&lt;/i&gt; of the late 19th century.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=indented&gt;As Benjamin points out and I exemplify with my tone and perception, this auratic nature puts rose-colored glasses on history itself.  Remember that the painting is a physical embodiment of history, yet, we treat that embodiment as ceremoniously sacred as if it were the ark of the covenant.  Thus, we associate that history with awe and rapturous majesty.  Seen this way, history, the world of the past, is no longer a brutish and lamentable existence.  It can no longer be seen for what it was: an archaic set of Hegelian &lt;i&gt;aufhebens&lt;/i&gt;. Instead, it becomes an ethereal dreamland of utopia and ardor.  In other words, seen through an auratic lexicon, in history, we have already reached our desired socio-political destination, which in turn confuses our perception of the present.  Under this disillusionment of aura, we as a social corpus are straight-jacketed, because, “...this mode of reception gives the masses no means of organizing and regulating their response” (36).  How can we politically engage with our present, if we don’t know where the present relates to its history?  But as I left that room starry-eyed and intoxicated, I stepped downstairs into the photography exhibit, and when I did, I crossed a historical-technological rubicon that for Benjamin, would shake me out of my historical-political stupor (19-20).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=indented&gt;This is because photography is less auratic than historical paintings.  Indeed, I have felt this truth ever since my first visits to the Getty as a schoolboy.  In my experience,  the Center for Photographs was nothing more than the center for yawns, likely because I had never, “ask[ed] the more fundamental question of whether the invention of photography had not transformed the entire character of art…” (28).  It is with these low expectations that I entered the photography gallery.  I glanced at the entranceway informing me that the exhibit was on Oscar Rejlander.  This name carried with it a complete absence of aura, but nonetheless, I carried on.  The room was poorly lit and large.  The first wall I looked at had a photograph of Rejlander’s wife—I yawned.  I next saw some cliché photos of nude models—my eyes glazed over.  It was starting to feel like one of those occasions where one feigns interest out of respect to some unknown ideal principle.  Then from the poorly lit room, I saw an entryway into a small,  slightly better-lit room.  I entered.  More nudes.  More yawns.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=indented&gt;But then, again on the back wall, I saw something intriguing.  I don’t recall why it caught my eye, but it certainly wasn’t aura—it was something else.  It was a photograph, but this photograph was different.  It was a scene—a montage.  The photo had a dynamic depth and width.  About two-dozen or more subjects strewn about in what can only be described as orderly chaos.  Yes, there were more bare breasts, but there were also people clothed.  People laying on the ground, sitting, and standing.  Mild captivation and the thirst for more crept into my mind.  I wasn’t experiencing the auratic cult value of the paintings, but instead, I was experiencing exhibition value—value in perception alone.  This is because, “[i]n photography, exhibition value begins to drive back cult value on all fronts” (27).  The aura that derived from the cult value of historical paintings gives way to a more clear-headed and phenomenological exhibition value of photographs.  As such, photographs, “...unsettle the viewer; he feels challenged to find a particular way to approach them” (27).  It had “become obligatory,” for me to find the description, and I did (27).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=indented&gt;This description informed me that the piece was titled, &lt;i&gt;The Two Ways of Life&lt;/i&gt;.  It depicted two young men on either side of an old sage.  The young man to the viewers left was jerking like an uncontrollable chariot horse towards a sinful and profane life before him, as depicted by a somewhat bacchanalian spectacle of nude women and debaucherous men.  The young man to the viewers right maintained composure like a noble chariot horse, his dignified chest opened towards a scene of divine virtue.  The sage, like a grappling charioteer, was worriedly focused on the nearly lost young man. The description explained that this was not just one photograph. Instead, it was a strategically arranged collage of over thirty negatives, each one focusing on a different character in the scene.  The result was a fluid and dynamic photography montage, that captured reality in a way that none of the paintings upstairs could have.  The spectacle was so tangible and vivid, but I knew (only because the description told me) that it was anything but fluid.  Instead, it was a carefully crafted and manicured scene.  Interestingly, right next to this photograph was an enlarged replicate, flying in the face of the paintings upstairs which could never be replicated (21).  Undeniably, what this piece lacked in aura, it made up for in palpability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=indented&gt;Benjamin wants to uncover why that is.  The short answer is that photography is an art form of technological reproducibility, and, “...the technological reproduction of artworks is something new,” when compared to the archaic cult-value artwork upstairs (20).  In the photograph, “[t]he finished film is the exact antithesis of a work created in a single stroke,” like the single strokes that once and forever created &lt;i&gt;Irises&lt;/i&gt; (28).  Thus, the physical import of the piece washes away (22)&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;. Benjamin is highlighting how unlike the paintings of Van Gogh, which is a spontaneous and inescapably unique gesture, the photograph (and movie) is an orchestrated scene.  If Rejlander didn’t like a certain arrangement of negatives, all he had to do was readjust.  This stands in stark opposition to Van Gogh, who in no way can adjust a brush stroke once laid down.  The paintings are unique moments captured forever on a canvas, while a photograph or film-reel is a carefully arranged and edited scene or series of scenes.  This facet of photography and other technologically reproducible art forms, “...transformed the entire character of art (28).”  It replaced amazing aura with tractability over reality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=indented&gt;And again, this has political import for Benjamin.  Whereas we had previously been awe-struck and straight-jacketed by the aura of the historical painting, as it tinted our lexicon via rose-colored glasses, the opposite is true for the arts of technological reproduction.  For these art forms, we are shaken out of our stupor and given chisels with which to sculpt our reality.  We cease being spectators and become actors.  Technologically reproducible art, because of its ability to shape a moment in reality, reveals to us that our world is not complete, never has been complete, and can only be completed through creation in the present.  It, “...create[s] a demand whose hour of full satisfaction has not yet come” (38).  For Benjamin, “[t]hese defining developmental tendencies of [technologically reproducible] art can therefore contribute to the political struggle in ways that it would be a mistake to underestimate” (19-20).  Indeed, under these technological advancements, “...the whole social function of art is revolutionized.  Instead of being founded on ritual, it is based on a different practice: politics” (25).  Again, why?  Because politics is the vehicle for change via rearrangement and restructuring.  Technological reproducible art forms, like photography and film, artistically exemplify and demonstrate this restructuring process.  Thus, “&lt;i&gt;...they are useful for the formulation of revolutionary demands in the politics of art&lt;/i&gt;” (20).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=indented&gt;According to Benjamin, what intrigued me most about The &lt;i&gt;Two Ways of Life&lt;/i&gt;, was not its unique and original spatiotemporal qualities but rather, its structured, real-life qualities, that, for a moment at least, allowed my world to blend with its, and in that blending, my world realized the same plastic quality that the photograph realized.  “&lt;i&gt;The most important social function of film is to establish equilibrium between human beings and the apparatus&lt;/i&gt;” (37)&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;.  Of course, he considered this process to be a mostly subconscious one, but for him, it is in the subconscious where spatiotemporal realities are at their most vulnerable to re-evaluation (37).  I actually didn’t want to leave that back wall, but I knew I had to eventually, lest I turn into Lot’s wife upstairs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=indented&gt;It was time for me to get going, but I fancied a stop at the gift shop on my way out.  I enjoyed the Manet, Monet, and Rejlander pieces so much, I wanted them for myself—at least a copy.  I found the first two, but not the Rejlander, and as I type right now, the Manet and the Monet prints stare at me on an adjacent wall in my bedroom.  I wanted to get closer to the art, I wanted to get closer to the world.  But in the end, it was &lt;i&gt;The Two Ways of Life&lt;/i&gt; that afforded me that closeness, and the only thing the prints on my wall can afford me is eye candy and a portal to a good memory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;sub&gt;1. While I did walk past statues of the likes of Apollo and Dionysus, it is safe to say that not a single person among the hoards that day were actually on a Delphi-like spiritual pilgrimage to pay tribute to those gods, as they may have in ancient Greece.&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;sub&gt;2. I would be remiss if I didn’t clarify that here, Benjamin is referring to cinema as the true antithesis to auratic art, but I'm focusing on photography, which is the technological precursor to film, and thus, all important attributes of cinema apply to photography, just in a less mature form.
&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;sub&gt;3. See footnote 2&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="philosophy"></category></entry><entry><title>Freedom Flowers: How One Woman Exemplified an Entire Generation’s Liberation</title><link href="/freedom-flowers.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-12-22T10:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2018-12-22T10:00:00-08:00</updated><author><name>Gregory Alonge</name></author><id>tag:None,2018-12-22:/freedom-flowers.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;style&gt;
  .indented {
    text-indent: 30pt;
  }
&lt;/style&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=indented&gt;Without a good seed, soil, water, and sunlight, a rose will never bloom.  The same is true of a free-spirited woman.  In order for her to truly prosper, she needs an environment of liberty for her inner seed to grow into a flower of freedom.  Yet up until the 1960’s, very few if any American women were actually given this encouraging environment, leading to generation after generation of oppressed persons—good seeds that were never given soil, water or sunlight.  But that began to change in the 1960’s when finally, American culture began to properly …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;style&gt;
  .indented {
    text-indent: 30pt;
  }
&lt;/style&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=indented&gt;Without a good seed, soil, water, and sunlight, a rose will never bloom.  The same is true of a free-spirited woman.  In order for her to truly prosper, she needs an environment of liberty for her inner seed to grow into a flower of freedom.  Yet up until the 1960’s, very few if any American women were actually given this encouraging environment, leading to generation after generation of oppressed persons—good seeds that were never given soil, water or sunlight.  But that began to change in the 1960’s when finally, American culture began to properly nurture the independence of women.  One such woman, was and is Marlene Baddin.  She, was a seed of innate drive, that was planted by her parents in the soil of the zeitgeist; which then received water in the form of subversive television, and sunlight in the form of West Los Angeles feminism.  Her rose was just one of many in a vast bloom of an entire generation.  The result was the first American generation in US history of truly liberated women, who fought against the gross excesses of capitalism and consumerism that created oppressive gender roles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=indented&gt;Marlene Baddin was born in Fresno California, 1951.  She grew up in a Jewish middle-class family of four with her parents and little brother.  Her parents, who no doubt embodied the contemporary popular mind, had the greatest influence on Marlene of anybody.  She had a loving relationship with both of them; but tragically, her father passed away when she was only seventeen, devastating the family.  Her father was an academic and respected professional symphony musician across the bay area.  Marlene remembers him lovingly, emphasizing that he was an enlightened artist with a great sense of humor.  Her mom was the wife of an academic who rotated with the other wives to host elaborate social functions.  She was everything Marlene and her brother could want in a mom—a fun, warm, and intelligent women even to this day.  Marlene remarks that both her parents were easy going people of a liberal mindset.  However, while her mother wanted to go to college and finish her degree, her “father was…you know, of that era where women stayed home and did not work.  My mother wanted to go back to school, but he didn’t let her” (Baddin).  In the 1950’s, the man’s need to be the one and only breadwinner was still overwhelmingly strong because of strict suburban middle-class gender roles.  Marlene’s father was adhering to pre-established gender roles—not out of malice, but out of social influence.  He wanted to live a traditional life, with his traditional wife.  Why?  Because he believed that is what brought happiness.  But according to leading philosopher of this time Herbert Marcuse, while heavily gendered consumer culture grew within middle-class families, happiness did not (xviii).  Marlene’s father sensed this, and did not want the same oppressive gender roles for his daughter.  She explains, “It was interesting.  Even though he wouldn’t let my mother go to college, there was no question about [me getting] my education” (Baddin).  Deep down he sensed what Marcuse articulated—that the traditional gendered society hinders happiness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=indented&gt;In addition to Marcuse, Simone De Beauvoir’s influence on the mid-20th century zeitgeist is unquestioned.  Her effect on American culture in is just one example of a philosopher helping to shift the popular mindset.  Other such impactful people include Karl Marx, Allen Ginsberg, the aforementioned Herbert Marcuse, and Cesar Chavez.  We know these thinkers affected Marlene growing up when she says, “I was really into poetry, and I was really into the philosophers of the time” (Baddin).  De Beauvoir and the other great thinkers’ influence began to awaken people across the globe to how a woman can actually be liberated, including Marlene’s parents and Marlene herself.  According to Ann Curthoys, the most influential aspect of De Beauvoir, more so than her words, was her real-life experiences as detailed through her autobiographies.  Curthoys makes it clear that what made De Beauvoir resonate, was that she walked the walk of an independent woman.  She details for us how De Beauvoir used to leave her house early on Thursday and Sunday mornings winter or summer, and often return home late at night (7).   Chronicled in her autobiography “The Prime of Life,” De Beauvoir writes, “I didn’t bother with all the preliminaries…I would slip on an old dress and a pair of espadrilles, and take a few bananas and buns with me in a basket” (77).  She went out on walks regularly regardless of weather—weather was not stopping her.  She came home when she wanted—time was not constraining her.  She wore a comfortable dress—clothes would not restrict her (unlike her Victorian predecessors).  Furthermore, De Beauvoir was expected to marry, have kids, and rear those kids. That she was doing none of these things illustrates just how subversive she was—and was happy to be.  Marlene’s parents absorbed this model for women to be free and happy, and they wanted it for Marlene.  That, is why her dad wanted her to go to college even though he did not want his wife to.  He knew that Marlene would be happier given the freedom De Beauvoir had.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=indented&gt;In the 1960’s, even the television of Marlene’s teenage years became a pointed attack on traditional suburban, middle-class values.  In order to understand 1960’s TV, one must first understand the suburbanization of America in the 1950’s.   In Laura Morowitz’ article, she details the mass migration of middle-class families into the suburbs.  In this era, more than half of the sitcoms released were “Leave It to Beaver” style shows—depictions of a suburban family, going through suburban daily life.  Then, “A medium first marketed as family entertainment, aimed at selling consumer products to growing families...” (36) The medium did this because the economic opportunity was there, and in a capitalist system, every economic opportunity must be exploited&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;.  In summary, the families moved into the suburbs, and started watching TV shows about families in the suburbs.  This left the door open for advertisers to sell their suburban products to the families, which created an environment where “it seemed that television, suburbia, consumerism and the domestic sitcom were all inherently intertwined” (36).  This suburban family consumer culture was gender oppressive, meaning both men and women were restricted by gender molds that came out of the suburban structure.  Specifically, men had to be breadwinners, who woke up early, shaved their face, read the morning newspaper and then went off to work for a boss at a menial desk job.  The woman was expected to marry one of these poor saps, and be his domestic goddess—she who keeps everything clean, calm, cool and collected—all while wearing high heels and a nice dress.  These suffocating gender boxes led to mass oppression&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;.  Counter culture, and the subsequent Women’s Liberation Movement, ‘hippie’ scene, sexual revolution and other cultural movements, were the direct result of this oppression; according to both leading thinkers of that time like Marcuse and De Beauvoir, and leading academics of modern times, like James Suri and Laura Morowitz (Celarant 42, Marcuse 91, Morowitz 36, Suri 49).  As Morowitz points out, TV shows like, “The Munsters” and “The Adams Family,” replaced the 1950s “Leave it To Beaver” shows, and took direct shots at the idealized suburban American family architype (35, 49).  These new shows of the 60’s depicted families that did not fit into the oppressive gender boxes; yet, they still managed to be lovable and relatable.  When Marlene and other impressionable teenage girls saw these subversive shows, for the first time in American history, they were being sent the message: IT IS OKAY TO BE DIFFERENT.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=indented&gt;At the age of eighteen after graduating high school, Marlene was ready to leave her small town of Fresno, and go to college, so she left for Los Angeles with a clear sense of identity and purpose.  Upon arrival in West Los Angeles, she was pleasantly surprised to see that her new environment was a safe haven for free-spirits like herself.  We know West LA was such a place because a local school, University High School, was undergoing its own major feminism movement called, “The Red Tide.”  This was a local, primarily student driven movement, but faculty and community members no doubt played a major supporting role.  Matthew Ides details that, “Red Tide members were agents of enlistment, and Uni High and West Los Angeles served as the recruitment site”(298).  This is not to suggest that Uni High students were recruiting women across the globe like college football coaches.  Rather, it shows that the cultural shift towards women’s liberation was widespread.  West Los Angeles via the Red Tide, was a place where women of all ages took a stand for what they believed in, and talked about issues that concerned them, like abortion rights and equal pay.  For the first time, Teenage girls and women across the country were not summarily shunned for talking about previously taboo topics.  For Marlene, moving to a place like West Los Angeles, where the Red Tide movement was a symbol of women fighting for liberation, allowed her to further cultivate her own free will.  In other words, West Los Angeles provided the much-needed sunlight that gave Marlene’s flower of freedom a true chance to grow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=indented&gt;Separate from her environment, Marlene reports having an innate personality that is independent and adventurous.  She values travel, education, creativity and entrepreneurship—in a word: liberation.  She explains, “I was never a joiner.  I never liked being in a group kind of thing, it was never ideal” (Baddin).  It is not that she was aloof; but rather, she was a free-spirit, who never enjoyed regimented mandates, or structured paths.  Marlene’s major life decisions exemplify both her personality, and her generation’s newly encouraged mindset.  In the mid-seventies, a few years after marrying her first husband ‘Rich,’ the two of them decided that Rich would open up his own seafood market, while Marlene would help bankroll the endeavor.  Fortunately, the seafood market was a success.  Unfortunately, when Marlene expressed her desire to open up her own branch of the business, Rich “…wasn’t having any part of it.  He wanted me to be Mrs. ‘fresh fish and seafood market,’ and go to mommy and me’s, and blah blah blah, and I was like…Huh?” (Baddin) Why was Rich not supportive?  Because he wanted his family to fit the pre-1960’s American architype.  He believed that if Marlene opened her own business, his ideal family would be lost.  It was the same dynamic as her father not wanting her mother to get her degree, only this time, the woman in the dynamic did not comply.  Marlene left Rich, and she cites this as the large straw that broke the proverbial camel’s back: “A great deal of the reason that ‘Rich’ and I weren’t able to stay together was because I think I was growing in a more liberated way as a woman, and I felt that he was holding me back” (Baddin).  Her wings would not be clipped, and she was going to make sure of it.  Marlene, and the women of her generation were making self-affirming life decisions, making them the first generation of American women to fight back en masse against the suffocating molds of archaic femininity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=indented&gt;The evidence for Marlene’s innate grit and independence continues.  By the time Marlene was 30, she was a single woman (by her own choosing) with a 3-year-old son.  These single mothers were, and still are stigmatized with various prejudices, a leading one being that all single women struggle to survive financially and raise a child adequately.  This preconceived notion of a single mom’s frailty certainly did not apply to Marlene, and one study suggests that middle-class single mothers persevere as a group more often than not.  The study found that “Single mothers are generally resilient…identify themselves as strong and able to achieve goals…reported that they try their best…[and]said that they were proud of achievements and believe past successes give them the ability to be successful in the future” (Kjellstrand, Harper 323).  Overall, single mothers in this study were strong, capable and confident women.  They certainly were not the pitiful image of an overwhelmed mother.  Rather, they were in control, and in a loving and ambitious way.  The same was true of Marlene.  She confided in me that she was indeed her son’s breadwinner, and she always provided food, insurance and all the basic comforts in life for the two of them.  She also told me that she always had a close, trusting relationship with her son (Baddin).  Marlene, not unlike the majority of middle-class single mothers, was beyond capable, and the American public was starting to see it with their own eyes for the first time in the second half of the 20th century.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=indented&gt;The 1960’s and onward proved to be the first era in this country’s history that enabled free-spirited women like Marlene Baddin to be given legitimate encouragement to live liberated.  This came about through a shift in the environment caused, by the excesses of consumerism, that resulted in a change in popular mind and culture.  However, this is not to imply that we live in an egalitarian society in which men and women are treated equally, and there are no gender roles at all.  We have a long way toward equality, but America took the true first steps in the 1960’s, when the American people collectively shifted their attitudes on what it meant to be a truly free person—woman or man.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;sub&gt;1. According to Marx.  I believe Marcuse would agree.  I tend to agree as well.&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;sub&gt;2. Keep in mind that the horrors of the holocaust made powerful American government and corporate figures fear the collective subconscious.  Beyond gender roles, all behavior was strictly monitored and controlled.  To illustrate how, would be beyond the scope of this paper, but for now, you can look up both “Control Your Emotions, A Coronet Film,” and “The Century of the Self,” on any accessible video-streaming platform. &lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="philosophy"></category></entry><entry><title>Eros as an Active Force in The Will To Power</title><link href="/eros-as-an-active-force.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-11-05T10:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2018-11-05T10:00:00-08:00</updated><author><name>Gregory Alonge</name></author><id>tag:None,2018-11-05:/eros-as-an-active-force.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Long before Plato, indeed, long before even the pre-Socratics, Hesiod’s Theogony declared Eros as one of the four principal deities responsible for shaping our universe.  He considered it to be the fairest of the deities, responsible for our sexual desire and urge to reproduce[1].  By the time Plato takes on the topic it has changed slightly, but what's clear, is that Eros was a pervasive concept that garnered thought and reverence from the greatest of thinkers.  Plato, through Socrates, discusses Eros in his dialogue, &lt;em&gt;Phaedrus&lt;/em&gt;.  A dynamic dialogue, &lt;em&gt;Phaedrus&lt;/em&gt; focuses on philosophical communication by using Eros as the …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Long before Plato, indeed, long before even the pre-Socratics, Hesiod’s Theogony declared Eros as one of the four principal deities responsible for shaping our universe.  He considered it to be the fairest of the deities, responsible for our sexual desire and urge to reproduce[1].  By the time Plato takes on the topic it has changed slightly, but what's clear, is that Eros was a pervasive concept that garnered thought and reverence from the greatest of thinkers.  Plato, through Socrates, discusses Eros in his dialogue, &lt;em&gt;Phaedrus&lt;/em&gt;.  A dynamic dialogue, &lt;em&gt;Phaedrus&lt;/em&gt; focuses on philosophical communication by using Eros as the subject matter.  For the scope of this piece, I will be outlining how Plato defines Eros, and how he suggests it interacts with our lives.  As I do so, I will also be highlighting how Plato’s description of Eros thus renders it an active force in the Nietzschean will to power dynamic.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;
    It is in Socrates’ famous second speech that the concept of Eros is outlined and is thus made clear to be an active force in the will to power.  He does this by equating love to a blessed madness and then describing the derivation of this madness.  To do this, he employs a grand metaphor that goes as follows: all souls are a pair of two horses, and one charioteer at the reins.  All gods are composed of two beautiful, strong and disciplined horses; while all mortal souls have one good horse, and one bad horse.  For us mortals, our souls constantly struggle with our one bad horse.  Before going further, we must define the Nietzschean will to power.  According to Gilles Deleuze, “We know that the will to power is the differential element, the genealogical element which determines the relation of force with force...” (62).  Here, we see the ‘differential element’ in the two contrasting horses of the mortal souls.  The two horses are like opposing forces, the strong horse as an active force, and the weak horse as the reactive force.  Through our discussion of Eros, we will see this interplay between the two forces play out, thus rendering it a will to power[2].&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;
    Socrates declares that all souls belong to the heavens, and initially exist in winged disembodied states.  In their original state, these souls patrol the heavens, feasting on beauty, truth, and piety.  However, when these souls are starved of their nourishment, their wings begin to die and fall off.  So where do they find such sustenance?  Socrates explains this by using captivating imagery.  He tells us that in the realm of the heavens, there lies an elevation which leads to the summit of the heavens[3].  In one tragic procession, the gods lead the way and quickly ascend the mighty elevation and feast on the nourishment that lies in the grasses beyond the heavens.  Following the gods are the mortal souls, who have a more difficult time ascending the elevation, for their ugly horse makes the journey cumbersome.  Only the skilled charioteer who can manage his bad horse can reach the summit.  Even so, once at the summit, the ugly horse occasionally jerks the charioteer away from viewing the beyond heaven.  None the less, this charioteer still gets to see some aspects of the beyond, and his horses get adequate nourishment from it.  Last in the procession of heavenly souls are the mortal souls who cannot control their sick horses.  The repugnant horse is winning the struggle, and thus, these chariots are never able to summit.  Not only are these souls struggling with their bad horse, but they are also fighting with other defeated souls.  As a result, they never feast on the truth and beauty that lies beyond the heavens, and instead nourish themselves with petty opinions, superstition, and conjecture.  Thus, their wings begin to die off, and they fall to earth where they attach to a physical body.  Here we see that all souls are a will to power composed of an interplay between differing forces.  The active force is the strong horse, while the reactive force is the weak horse.  In the gods, there is no duality of differential forces because they are gods.  For the mortals, only those who are god-like (Übermenschen) realize a dominance of active forces and submission of reactive forces.  The mortals whose souls never reach the summit have a will to power in which the reactive forces disintegrate the active forces, thus becoming defeated by baseness.  Deleuze outlines this when he says, “But an inferior force can bring about disintegration or splitting of superior forces…” (63)  Crucially, this still defines a will to power, but this will to power is now slavish, just as the defeated mortal soul is a slave to the vile horse.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;
    However, what does Eros have to do with an interplay of the soul?  Well, Eros is an active force.  It is one of the beautiful truths that lie beyond heaven visible from the summit.  Indeed, it is the most beautiful of all truths and shines radiantly.  Philosophically speaking, it is one of Plato’s forms, all of which lie here, beyond the heavens.  These forms are eternally true essences.  For Plato, everything has an essence, and when we experience a thing on earth, we are merely experiencing the representation of that essence.  Moreover, the form exists with or without the representation of it.  Recall that our souls began as winged spirits of the heaven who feasted upon the forms beyond heaven.  Therefore, when we experience an essence on earth, we remember the experience of that essence in the beyond heaven—an experience that we have not been nourished by since our time as winged chariots.  Therefore, when we experience true beauty, we are jolted back to a recollection of the magnificent form of Eros.  This puts us in a state of awe.  Our poor, debilitated souls are stricken with terror, just as suffocating lungs violently gasp for air when relieved.  The experience pulls us out of our dark cave—a cave we thought constituted our entire reality.  It connects us to a beauty we forgot existed, leading us to the light beyond the cave entrance[4].  In this moment of recognition, he who undergoes this experience is, “...reminded of true beauty...and he gazes aloft, like a bird, paying no attention to what is down below—and that is what brings on him the charge that he has gone mad” (37).  This is why being in love is a blessed madness.  Ultimately, this blessed madness is an active force which seeks to dominate the soul of the lover.  However, what is the reactive force which aims to destroy the active Eros?  Chaos.  Chaos is the reactive and submissive force which dances in the duality, and insidiously threatens the dominance of Eros in the will to power.  Which is appropriate, for the father of Eros in the Theogony is chaos, another principle deity in Hesiod's cosmogony.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;
    The chaotic force is outlined in Lysias’ speech.  In his speech, Lysius presents the soul of the lover as having been consumed by the reactive force of chaos.  Thus, Lysius paints the lover as a slave to his own base desires and interests, as someone who has lost all control.  This base lover is selfish, possessive and hedonistic.  He does not want what is best for the beloved; rather, he wants his animal flesh to be satisfied at the certain expense of the beloved’s well-being.  This is because the reactive chaos has overwhelmed the active Eros, and “[w]hen reactive force separates active force from what it can do, the latter also becomes reactive.  &lt;em&gt;Active forces become reactive&lt;/em&gt;” (Deleuze, 64).  Thus degrading the active force of Eros into a reactive force of greedy obsession—the pathetic version of itself.  The strong horse of our soul has been turned into the wretched horse in our will to power.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;
    Socrates acknowledges this danger that the lover faces.  He recognizes that every soul is nothing more than a will to power, where active forces battle reactive forces for dominance.  However, for Socrates, just as on the path to philosophy, the path to true love, is one in which beauty overcomes chaos.  The chaos remains, just like our ugly horse, but it is now submissive and tractable again.  It is now contained enough to ascend the heavenly elevation, thus affording the charioteer “Another becoming, another sensibility: the overman” (Deleuze, 65).&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;
    It is now time to outline the experience of the lover and the beloved when their wills to power encounter these forces.  According to Plato, beauty, and thus the forces it generates, engages the soul via our eyes.  The lover sees beauty gleaming in a beautiful person.  This is the moment when the lover undergoes his profound recollection of beauty’s essence, affecting a sharp pain.  It is the pain of his soul’s wings beginning to grow back, and from here on, the lover is caught in the rapture of the beloved’s physical beauty.  The lover cannot stop thinking about his beloved, so he seeks her out at every possible opportunity.  When the lover is with his beloved, he feels the intense mollification of his painful abscesses where wings once were.  Conversely, when he is away from his beloved, the pain becomes unbearable.  Only the vision and presence of his beloved can adequately soothe his agony.  Thus, even the potential of encountering his beloved stokes a frenzy within him that reverberates through his entire soul.  Each time he sees her, his chariot is violently pulled toward her by his untamed horse of chaos.  His vile horse bucks in a fury, and throws the charioteer off the chariot.  The force of the ugly horse has brought the chariot to within inches of the beloved’s face.  The charioteer, in awe of the pure beauty before him, is overcome with terror, and in so being, realizes a superhuman strength.  In an epic struggle, the charioteer bloodies and injures the ignoble horse to such an extent, that it finally submits.  It relents to the charioteer.  The active force has dominated the reactive force in the lover’s will to power.  Now the lover has regained control, and in so doing, can share his love with his beloved in a way that elevates them both to the gods, thus following the gods to the summit of the heavens, and nourishing their souls on the manna of the forms.  “This is the experience we humans call love…” (41)&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;
    As for the beloved, she notices her lover’s gaze upon her, but is initially reticent, for she must wait to see how her lover’s will to power manifests itself in its sensibility.  Eventually, when the active Eros of the lover has prevailed over the reactive chaos, she begins to notice the controlled elation signified in the lover’s eyes.  She sees these essences within him, and she becomes overtaken by her own will to power.  She begins to fall in love with the reflection of enchantment incandescent in the lover’s eyes.  She is caught up in the form of beauty as it shines upon her representation of it.  Eventually, she desires to spend more time with the lover, and she slowly begins to feel the active force of Eros overcome her soul as well.  When it finally does, she embraces the lover in a physical celebration of the most beautiful essence known in the cosmos.  The two become inseparable as they ascend the hierarchy of souls, reaching ever closer to the gods.  Such is Eros.  Two Übermenschen who’s souls continually and perpetually lift one another up in an eternal return of their respective affirming wills to power.  “...their life here below is one of bliss and shared understanding” (Phaedrus, 47)[5].&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;sub&gt;1. “In knowledge too, I feel only my will’s joy in procreating and becoming; and if there is innocence in my knowledge, it is because the will to procreation is in it” (Zarathustra II “On Blissful Isles”).&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;sub&gt;2. The will to power is often confused for a desire to dominate.  This, in the case of the Nietzschean concept, is a common and gross misinterpretation, the reasoning behind which goes beyond the scope of this project.
&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;sub&gt;3. “From afar we can hardly see the summit” (Deleuze, 71)&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;sub&gt;4. Plato’s &lt;i&gt;Allegory of the Cave&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;sub&gt;5.  For, “... [their] will always comes to [them] as [their] liberator and comforter.  Willing liberates: that is the true teaching of will and freedom…” (Zarathustra II “On Blissful Isles”)
&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="philosophy"></category></entry><entry><title>Situations and Choices: The Sum of Our Life as We Experience It</title><link href="/situations-and-choices.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-07-03T10:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2018-07-03T10:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Gregory Alonge</name></author><id>tag:None,2018-07-03:/situations-and-choices.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;i&gt;&lt;p align="center"&gt;“If the people of the world are plunged into yet another world war, the result will be that the Jews will take over even more” (Hitler, Jan 31st, 1941, right before Germany declared war on the Soviet Union).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;i/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As the existentialist Jean-Paul Sartre sees it, life centers around the choices we are free to make, and the situation from which we make those choices.  A Sartrean situation is the amalgamation of uncontrollable circumstances a person finds herself in, like her age, height, and yes, race.  According to the French philosopher and playwright, a human being is her situation, combined with …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;i&gt;&lt;p align="center"&gt;“If the people of the world are plunged into yet another world war, the result will be that the Jews will take over even more” (Hitler, Jan 31st, 1941, right before Germany declared war on the Soviet Union).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;i/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As the existentialist Jean-Paul Sartre sees it, life centers around the choices we are free to make, and the situation from which we make those choices.  A Sartrean situation is the amalgamation of uncontrollable circumstances a person finds herself in, like her age, height, and yes, race.  According to the French philosopher and playwright, a human being is her situation, combined with her choices.  Each choice she is presented with is an opportunity to create her path and shape her future from within her given situation.  But once she makes a choice, her decision is spot welded into her fixed situation.  All people choose what they want their lives to look like based on what their lives are not, and they choose their futures within the confines of their situation[1].  For example, the anti-Semite chooses to experience the world-view of a racist; and his situation—his age, genetic code, etc.—is incidental.  In his thrashing 1945 book, Anti-Semite and Jew, Sartre chooses to focus on the choices the anti-Semite makes, and the experience that follows from those choices.  Each decision rendered, effects ourselves, those around us, and the society at large, thus exposing the immense responsibility, and anguish[2] of life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For us to understand the chosen experience of the anti-Semite, we must first understand how the racist sees others around him.  We must uncover how he looks at the people in his frame of view at any one moment.  For Sartre, a large part of our situation is defined by how we are gazed upon, so, when the anti-Semite looks at a person, he, like everybody else, is partially determining that person’s situation.  If looked upon as Jewish, you are in the situation of a Jew.  If seen as black, you are in the situation of a black person.  The anti-Semite, who has chosen to scan for Jews and outsiders, looks out into the world and identifies a figure.  He then decides: Jew, or not Jew—one is either or.  Immediately thereafter, he deciphers: Frenchman, or not Frenchman—one is either or.  The bigot polarizes his vision via a black and white lexicon.  One of good vs. evil, Jew vs. non-Jew.  He evaluates with the nonsense of intuition, and stupidity of hatred and anger.  A ‘logic of passion.’  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A passion of cowardice he has chosen for himself and indulged to the fullest extent.  All passions are choices, but most are positive, like love and art.  The passion of anti-Semitism, on the other hand, is a negative passion of hatred, destruction, and rejection.  The racist’s negation assuages his hatred and justifies the mediocrity he has also chosen.  He has full control over his passion, as choices are tractable.  A member of the herd, the anti-Semite elects to be average, and thus takes refuge in comfort and ease.  His passion for mediocrity depends on his choice to be solid, stupid and stone-like.  Impenetrable and irrational to the point of delusion; because to be flexible, would require self-reflection—the very reflection he flees.  In choosing this experience, he runs away from his own contingency and responsibility.  He runs and hides from the fact that the world which does not need him, still requires responsibility of the choices thrust upon him.  In the reflection of the world’s indifference, the anti-Semite looks upon himself most vividly, and in his clairvoyance, chooses to deny.  He flees his consciousness, and thus existence[3].  He chooses to negate all other choices.  The cowardly racist denies himself, and in so doing, denies humanity—alas!  He still cannot escape the very anguish he originally fled.  He is a fearful and trembling[4] profile of his own shadow soaked in ressentiment[5].&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While falling into the abyss, the anti-Semite experiences the true indifference of the society.  He chooses to construct his own society in a fashion that accommodates his escape.  He chooses aristocracy.  This affords him free-superiority.  He has reified his status and encased it in a magical and timeless forcefield.  His preference for pre-revolution ways protects his mediocrity, and most importantly, his fearful escape from contingency and responsibility.  He chooses to construct a ‘pure’ and ‘righteous’ society, granting him the excuse to alienate and otherize.  His social construction is the barbiturate consciously taken to treat the anguish—the anguish that Sartre puts front and center throughout all his work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After picking up and absorbing Sartre’s Jew, the Martinican, Frantz Fanon, was inspired to write his own book in 1952, entitled, Black skins, White Masks.  In chapter five, “The Lived Experience of the Black Man,” instead of focusing on the choices a person makes as Sartre’s had, Fanon, focuses on the horrifying phenomenology of the black man.  His blackness induces this dreadful consciousness, which can only be excised with a full peel back of the skin from the flesh.  A white mask will not suffice.  The horrifying nature of the black man’s situation places it in the foreground of his lived experience.  Thus, Fanon redefines ontology as a structure shaped by the Sartrean look, which imposes a wretched lived experience and lays the stage for the choices we need to make freely.  Therefore, Fanon’s existence is dictated by an apparatus built from his oppressed situation.  This apparatus projects distinct looks onto him, which force him to choose his actions in the face of these hallucinogenic visuals.  This myopic schema comprises the lived experience of Frantz Fanon. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first look that Fanon receives as a black man is the white gaze.  It is a look of racism, which dehumanizes the colonized body, and dehumanizes Fanon with his penetrating gaze that objectifies[6], robbing him of the meaning he covets. 
Now, flayed open by the scalpel of the Eyes and exposed to the torrid radiation of the white gaze, his carcass is re-animated with savagery, cannibalism, fetishism and gaping white eyes.  The white man paints a grin on the wretched formation.  A shriek from the Other: 
“He’s scaring me, mama!” 
The white mass increases their distance but continues to stare.  Sensing solitude, Fanon hits the ground.  Manifest flesh and sinew covered by his own shadow—his back burns in the sun.  He shivers as he broils.  He chokes on the breathing room.  He sees the comedy and lives the tragedy.  The crowd stands at a distance, looking upon the figure with consternation, who collapses.  The crowd bolts, and once gone, the vultures circle overhead.
A lone woman enters Fanon’s field of perception.  Their eyes fasten—this look is different from the one the crowd had offered.  She comes over, picks him up off the ground, and helps him lick his wounds. 
“You see!”  She says, “Just because you’re a handsome Negro is no reason to fear you.” 
“The handsome Negro says, ‘Fuck you,’ Madame” (94). 
Her countenance tightens.  His blackness shouts through her vision—he sees her seeing it.  She runs away with the rest of them, and Fanon hits the ground again, but this time harboring a guttural roar.  Alone again, night descends, and he looks over himself.  One must imagine Fanon happy.[7]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He starts back for the town but knows that his undeniable blackness will spot him in a hurry.  He sees a Jewish brother crawling past.  The strophe calls out:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Brother.  Won’t they see you?” 
“Maybe.”  The antistrophe calls back. 
“What about me?” 
“You?  You are black.” &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fanon retreats and finds a wide gorge with rock enclaves splintering the earth.  Shelter for the evening.  There, he sees three other black men.  Not in person, but their thetics on the escarpments.  Written in a blue brought from the ocean and red risen from the earth, it reads: ‘Négritude.’  Fanon looks at the missives.  He reads, dissects, and rereads them.  Backward.  He is distrustful.  These colorful words look back at him in yet a third distinct fashion.  His eyes wide open and feet bare on the terrain, an empyreal rhythm establishes between him, the paints, and cosmos.  Grounded and free.  Mind and body reunified—this experience is compelling.  The poetic opium stirs his passion.  “This! —is verse.”  A sensitive verse yet to breathe warm air into the cold and cataloged nitrogen, oxygen, and argon of the library in town.  He knew it was black poetry, written by black people, for black people.  Prose gazing upon him—he chooses pride, staring straight into the paint’s eyes.  He chooses superiority.  Affirms his blackness.  All the culture negated can now be accepted.  Again, the night fell, exposing himself to himself in the mirror of the void.  Strength peaked, tomorrow, he would venture back into town and share his dream.[8]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The next dawn, with a new sun and rejuvenating experience, Fanon leaves the comforting shelter of négritude and makes his way down the exposed tundra back for town.  The slight chill on his back signals both a drop in altitude; and a man with a lazy-eye, black spectacles, and black book in hand sitting near a stone.  It was Sartre, who immediately stares into Fanon’s eyes with a fourth, penetrating gaze that freezes him in his tracks.  The gaze sounds the depths of the unified mind-body schema.  He scowls back and attempts to carry on, but Sartre blocks his path.  Standing there, he opens the book which has the word ‘Orpheus,’ inscribed on it, and says:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have been to the massif you return from, and oh what a beautiful rock it is.  What colors and rhythms and prose!  You will go back into town, and tell them of the fracture the canyon carves, and indeed, they will see you.  They may even see you differently.  But alas!  Remember, that your antithesis will be quartered and drawn for the fulfillment of the necessary Promethean Synthesis!  After tirelessly separating each limb from your corpus, they will drag your entrails along the cobblestone road out of town for everyone to see your destruction fade into the horizon, and they will see—your solubility.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fanon gapes ahead as Sartre carries on,
  I remember when I was naive like you.  One day, you will come to understand as I did, my boy.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fanon stands up, and on two solid feet, shouts back at him:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“White man!  In the midst of battle, the soldier cannot contemplate the war!”  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just moments before, he had been unbridled and celestially impulsive.  Now, he could
feel the weight mounting on his feet.  The white Frenchman stares unflinchingly into Fanon’s fractured unity.  Still on his feet, he continues forward, down into the swampy town shouting:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Fuck you, Sartre!  I needed not to know!”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just outside town, a drunken vagrant in an old shivering wheelchair, bitterly calls out to catch the fast-paced Fanon’s ear:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Heyh!  Doan chu know?  Their gonna to do to yew what they di’ tah meh!  ‘We are both casualties”’ (119).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fanon evades the derelict eyes and hurries his pace.  His inner orb focusing on the astral-terra synesthesia, he stops, tilts his eyes closed to the sky, and shouts from his knees:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I will turn over each element of the cosmos before I concede!”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;sub&gt;1. “We are what we are not, and we are not what we are.”&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;sub&gt;2. “The existentialists say at once that man is anguish.  What that means is this: the man who involves himself and realizes that he is not only the person he chooses to be, but also a lawmaker who is, at the same time, choosing all mankind as well as himself, cannot help escape the feeling of his total and deep responsibility” (Marino 347, excerpt from Existentialism is a Humanism).  Definite echoes of Kant’s 1st form categorical imperative.&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;sub&gt;3. He doesn’t lack &lt;em&gt;bewusstsein&lt;/em&gt; in the Marxian sense. Rather, he runs away from it because he is afraid, and thus has chosen to be a coward.&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;sub&gt;4. Fear and Trembling (1843) Søren Kierkegaard, widely seen as father of existentialism.&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;sub&gt;5. “...slave morality from the outset says No to what is “outside,” what is “different,” what is “not itself”...this need to direct one’s view outward instead of back to oneself—is the essence of ressentiment…” (Ch. 10 On the Genealogy of Morals, Nietzsche)&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;sub&gt;6. The white gaze violates Kant’s 2nd form categorical imperative.&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;sub&gt;7. “One must imagine Sisyphus happy.”&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;sub&gt;8. I woke this morning with my mind&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;sub&gt;Set on Freedom.&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;sub&gt;Hallelu, Hallelu, Hallelujah!  -One of the gospel hymns that rang out as marchers on Washington poured out of their trains and buses in 1963, to see Dr. King Jr. tell the people, about his dream. (Hansen The Dream 34)
&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="philosophy"></category></entry><entry><title>Situations and Choices: Preface</title><link href="/situations-and-choices-preface.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-07-02T10:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2018-07-02T10:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Gregory Alonge</name></author><id>tag:None,2018-07-02:/situations-and-choices-preface.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Why did Jean-Paul Sartre choose to write &lt;em&gt;Anti-Semite&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Jew&lt;/em&gt; in 1945?  Because he was pissed off.  He was angry at his native France for ignoring the problem.  At the conclusion of WWII, France was focusing on the positive, while trying to rebuild Europe.  Apparently, nobody wanted to broach the subject of millions of Jews being exterminated—but he did.  He felt obligated to explain to the population how and why anti-Semitism exists.  As a Jew myself, his words had an enormous impact on me, as he explained to me why my people have historically been scapegoated and discriminated.  He …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Why did Jean-Paul Sartre choose to write &lt;em&gt;Anti-Semite&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Jew&lt;/em&gt; in 1945?  Because he was pissed off.  He was angry at his native France for ignoring the problem.  At the conclusion of WWII, France was focusing on the positive, while trying to rebuild Europe.  Apparently, nobody wanted to broach the subject of millions of Jews being exterminated—but he did.  He felt obligated to explain to the population how and why anti-Semitism exists.  As a Jew myself, his words had an enormous impact on me, as he explained to me why my people have historically been scapegoated and discriminated.  He does this by breaking down the type of person who would choose to live with such extreme hatred.  His breakdown is outlined in my essay.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This breakdown shook the medical student Frantz Fanon to his core.  For the first time in his life, someone was sensibly explaining to him the nature of hatred and the type of person who harbors it.  However, while Fanon was captivated, he felt slightly unsatisfied.  Why?  Because Jews are essentially white people, so they are difficult to distinguish.  Black people like Fanon, on the other hand, could never blend into the white crowd. Therefore, the relentless hatred thrown his way was constant and debilitating.  That is why he wrote his book, Black Skins, White Masks in 1952.  It focuses on how black people live the experience of overwhelming racism, simply because their skin sets them starkly apart from the ruling white race.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I wrote this essay for people who study philosophy and history; however, I believe there is something to be gained by all readers.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="philosophy"></category></entry></feed>